[Music]
hey guys what's up Pastor Meers here and
uh I'm just dropping a quick video this
is going to be a response video um to a
uh video that was put up a few days ago
uh addressing the issue of the scapegoat
now I've already done an entire sermon
on this so if you haven't seen that I'm
going to encourage you to check that out
the the sermon is entitled um who is
Azazel or who is the
scapegoat but I just wanted to do this
followup only be a few minutes so won't
be long at all but uh before we get into
this video this response video um I want
to encourage you to like make sure you
like make sure you subscribe and um if
you want to support power of the Lamb
Ministries look in the link for the
patreon link uh that is going to be the
best way you can support this ministry
and help us to continue uh putting forth
material that's going to help you and
strengthen your walk with Christ okay
so um I'm going to share a video uh I'm
not going to show the individual I just
want you to hear his voice um and I want
you to hear what he has to say about the
scapegoat and why he believes the
scapegoat is Jesus I'm going to come
back on other the end of the video and
I'm going to address that very point so
let's go ahead and take a listen who
this individual is is not important um
we just want to focus on what they are
saying all right so listen for the voice
and then I'll come back on the other end
check it
out entirey ritual symbolizes Jesus
Jesus is symbolized by the high priest
Jesus is symbolized by the goat that
died Jesus is symbolized by the goat
that was sent away to Bear the sins of
others in fact that's precisely what a
scapegoat is a scapegoat was an innocent
victim that's what a scapegoat is it's
an innocent victim that bears the guilt
the penalty the blame the shame of
others this could never brothers and
sisters be applied or said of Satan I
hope you really think about these things
okay so let's think about it as he said
I want you to note how he describes or
defines the scapegoat as someone who is
innocent that bears the guilt for
someone else uh a person who is
blameless that ba blames the guilt for
that bears the guilt for someone else
and therefore we know that this is what
Jesus did and therefore the scapegoat is
Jesus but there's a problem with that
and uh I want you to check out Leviticus
chapter 16:8 uh the Bible says here and
Aaron shall cast lots upon the Two Goats
one lot for the Lord and the other lot
for the scapegoat so the assumption is
that the word scapegoat here means a
person who is Innocent but Bears the
guilt and shame for someone else but
let's actually see what the word means
so here we have it on the screen as AEL
from it's from two words as or as
meaning goat and then the other word is
AAL uh Hebrew 235 that's the Strong's
number and I want you to check out what
this word actually means according to
the Strong's Concordance we'll also
going to look at the Browns uh uh Hebrew
dictionary and I want you to check out
again the meaning of this word so Goat
as and then AEL which literally means
means to go away hence the term depart
or to
disappear to
fail and then it kind of repeats right
to go to and
fro the word literally means to
disappear to go away or to
fail so the goat as a failure the goat
that disappears The Goat goat that goes
away now what about the Brown's
according to Brown's definition of the
word it again says to go to go away to
go about to be used up to be exhausted
to be gone
evaporated
H so in essence the term as AEL
literally in its definition has nothing
to do with an an innocent person taking
the
blame for someone
else an innocent person an innocent
being taking the blame for something
else that's not in the definition of
this word now I know what you're
thinking the word scap goat literally
means someone who is innocent and takes
the blame for somebody else someone
who's who is blamed falsely but hold
your
thoughts this word remember how told you
that the word also means fail we find
the very word used in job 14:1 as the
waters fail so that's AAL as the waters
fail from the sea and the flood decayeth
and drith up that's job Chapter 14 verse
11 uh let's look at this same verse in a
couple of different translations and
you'll see what I mean so in the
Brenton's translation it is translated
as for the sea wastes in length of time
BSB as the water disappears drb as if
the water should depart the tlv as
Waters evaporate as water evaporates so
what I want you to see here is how the
word is translated in different
translations wastes disappears depart
evaporate
fail the goat check this out y'all the
term then as AEL would literally mean
the goat of failure or the goat of
departure or the goat that evaporates or
the goat that
disappears now if we're going to say
that
Jesus is a symbol or Azazel symbolizes
Jesus this goat is a representation of
Jesus then you got to ask yourself how
is Jesus the goat of failure how is
Jesus the goat that departs how is Jesus
the goat that's that evaporates how is
Jesus the goat that
disappears that would be a very strange
way to refer to Jesus however if Azazel
is Satan as I demonstrated in the sermon
the link that I sh the sermon I shared
with you
earlier if you haven't seen it go check
it out let's read Ezekiel 28: 18 and 19
which speak about
Lucifer who wanted to be like God who
was without
blemish we read that in Ezekiel 28
notice Verse
18 it says thou has defiled thy
sanctuaries by the multitude of thine
iniquities by the iniquity of thy
traffic therefore will I bring forth a
fire from the midst of thee it shall
devour thee in other words you're going
to be evaporated it's going to devour
you and I will bring thee to ashes upon
the Earth in the sight of all them that
behold thee all they that Know Thee
among the people shall be as said thee
Thou shalt be a terror and never shalt
thou be anymore you are going to
disappear you are going to cease to be
you who are one time without spot
without wrinkle you who are one time
perfect in your ways Ezekiel 28 vers 14
onward you who were one time at one time
perfect you are going to become nothing
you're going to disappear you're going
to evaporate you're a failure you failed
in your mission
let's keep going the question then
becomes well where did the where did
this idea of an innocent person being
blamed for the guilty come in in this
word scap cold so let's break this down
William Tindale is responsible for
translating the Bible the first person
to translate the Bible from Hebrew and
Greek to English in 1530
and what Tindale did when it came to
Leviticus chapter
16 he translated the word Azazel in this
way in fact I'm just going to read it on
the
screen so it says here Christian
Traditions similarly acknowledged that
one goat was to be slaughtered for
atonement of the community but the
second goat bearing the community sins
was understood to have simply gone free
to have escaped
escaped let me say that word one more
time escaped Tindale named this goat the
not scapegoat but escape
goat which evolved later to be used as
scapegoat so let's break this down we're
going to go to tindell's Bible and I
can't read Old English but this is the
English they were using at the time why
we call it Old English okay so in
Leviticus chapter 16:8 it says an Arrow
cast lots over the goat one lot for the
Lord add another for a scap
Goot now you're looking at the word scap
goat and you're saying yes see it's
there tindel didn't say escape goat he
said scape goat in the Old English but
here's what I want you to notice in
verse 10 it says but the Goot on which
the lot fell
to
esape please note that the word scape
here in Old English is
escape therefore when he writes in verse
eight another for escape goat the term
literally means escape
goat not a escape goat but escape goat
the goat that
escaped the goat that went away the goat
That Got Away that
escaped death escaped the death
penalty was not
sacrificed the Old English word scaping
from the early 13th century means to
escape depart from and is shortened from
or is a shortened form of
Escape it was frequently used in Pros
until the late 17th century and by the
late 14th century it also uh and it also
meant avoid death Peril punishment or
other
danger so the
scapegoat when tindel translated it did
not mean an innocent person who takes
the blame or an innocent being that
takes the blame for someone else it was
the escape
goat so how did we come to the place
where we now say the word scapegoat
means an innocent person who blames who
or who Bears the guilt for someone else
well let's check this out last slide and
then we're wrapping this up AI just
check AI on this the term scap go was
later adopted in English in the 15th
century to refer to someone who was
punished or blamed for the mistakes or
wrongdoing of others initially the term
was used figuratively to describe
someone who bore the blame or punishment
for others but it wasn't necessarily
meant to imply innocence over time over
time one more time Over time however the
term took on a a more negative
connotation implying that the person
being blamed was indeed innocent and
being unfairly punished or criticized
for the action actions of
others this sense of Injustice and
unfairness is relatively is a relatively
recent development dating back to the
19th or early 20th century in Modern
English the term skategoat is often used
to describe a situation where an
individual or group is unfairly blamed
for the problems or failures of others
the usage is often associated with
psychological or social
dynamics where individuals or groups may
be targeted for blame or criticism due
to their perceived vulnerab
vulnerability powerlessness or lack of
resources so while the term scapegoat
has its roots in ancient Jewish rituals
its modern
connotation of unfairly blaming an
innocent person is a relatively recent
development so come on y'all listen
carefully here's what's happening
people are taking the modern
term of the word scapegoat which is
a incorrect understanding of what the
original term that was used by tindel
the
escapegoat and they're putting the
modern day reading or modern day
understanding of scapegoat and they're
saying they they're reading that modern
day reading back into the original text
and when you do that beloved you end up
with something that that is foreign to
the
Bible Leviticus chapter 16 was in no
way
indicating that the
scapegoat was innocent and bearing the
sins or bearing the sins of others
though it was innocent not at all not in
the text this is as AEL the goat of
failure the goat of departure the goat
that evaporates the goat that disappears
The Goat that that that
fails Jesus is not a failure Jesus did
the Bible specifically says that he will
not fail nor be discouraged till he have
set his ey his law in the Isles the goat
of failure is not the Lord's goat the
Lord's goat is not the goat of failure
the goat of failure does not
die is not offered up as a
sacrifice it is not the same part of a
sacrifice if it was there would be no
need to cast
lots none
whatsoever on the other days of
sacrifice there's no casting of
lots all kinds of different animals be
are being sacrificed we know all
pointing to Christ but this is the
singular case in which there are lots
cast between these two
goats so here's the
challenge the idea that the scapegoat is
an
innocent uh represents an innocent being
bearing the punishment for others is
foreign to the Bible please tell us
where you get that definition from in
the scriptures because it's not there
all right that's it y'all that's a wrap
we made this short um next time someone
comes to you with the scapegoat and this
is what it means remember this
information all right okay blessings y'
all and uh hopefully this this is
sticking right here and uh may God bless
you as you continue to
search and understand search for and
understand truth the truth of the word
of God till next time